CONSTANZA RODRIGUEZ PICEDA

Postdoctoral fellow in geocomputing and earthquake hazard

PERSONAL PROFILE

I am a Geophysicist with a research focus ranging from the impact of complex fault networks on earthquake processes to the relationship between lithospheric structure and observed seismic deformation. My work spans multiple scales, from simulating seismic cycles in faults to exploring the thermal and rheological aspects of the lithosphere through data driven numerical modeling. I utilize these models to evaluate seismic geohazards and understand the connection between lithospheric structure, complex fault geometries, and present-day deformation.

EDUCATION

2018-2022 PhD in Geophysics at University of Potsdam (Germany)

Advisors: Manfred Strecker and Magdalena Scheck-Wenderoth (Grade summa

cum laude). PhD Defense date: 29 April 2022

2011-2017 Degree in Geological Science at University of Buenos Aires, Argentina (Grade

8.9/10)

PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS

2022-present Postdoctoral researcher at University of Plymouth (United Kingdom)

• Build numerical models to investigate the role of fault networks with complex geometries in earthquake cycles

• Contribute to development of numerical code of earthquake cycles QDYN (FORTRAN/python/MATLAB)

• Conducted field work in Central Appenines (Italy) to survey active faults

2022-present Teaching assistant at University of Plymouth (United Kingdom)

Demonstrator in undergraduate-student field trips to the South-West of

England

2022 Visiting researcher at Geoazur (France)

2018-2022 Graduate student researcher at GFZ German Research Centre for

Geosciences/University of Potsdam (Germany)

• Conducted research in Geophysics to understand the link between the thermal and rheological state of the lithosphere and present-day deformation processes in the southern Central Andes

• Performed integration of geological and geophysical data into 3D subsurface models

· Carried out gravity-based, thermal and rheological modelling

• Publish findings in peer-reviewed journals and professional society meetings

Teaching assistant at University of Potsdam (Germany)

Assisted in the master course 'Neotectonics and Geodynamics'

2016-2017 Student field assistant at University of Buenos Aires (Argentina)

- Carried out geological and paleomagnetic surveys
- Sample processing using different paleomagnetic techniques (MSA, AF, HT, IRM)

SCIENTIFIC BACKGROUND

2020

• PUBLICATIONS	S IN REFEREED JOURNALS
Under review	Rodriguez Piceda, C. , Mildon, Z., van den Ende, M., Andrews, B., and Ampuero, J. P. Normal fault interactions in seismic cycles and the impact of fault network geometry. <i>Submitted to Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</i>
2023	Pons M., Rodriguez Piceda, C., Sobolev S., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., & Strecker, M. Localization of deformation in a non-collisional subduction orogen: the roles of dip geometry and plate strength on the evolution of the broken Andean foreland, Sierras Pampeanas, Argentina. <i>Tectonics</i>
2023	Rodriguez Piceda, C., Gao, Y., Cacace M., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Bott, J., Tilmann, F., & Strecker M., The role of mantle hydration and flexure on slab seismicity in the southern Central Andes. <i>Nature Communications Earth and Environment</i>
2022	Rodriguez Piceda, C., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Cacace M., Bott, J., & Strecker M., Long-term lithospheric strength and intraplate seismicity in the southern Central Andes (29°S-39°S). <i>Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems</i>
2022	Rodriguez Piceda, C., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Bott, J., Cacace, M., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Pons, M., Prezzi, C.B. & Strecker M., Controlling factors of an oceanic-continental subduction zone: the southern Central Andes. <i>Lithosphere</i>
2021	Barrionuevo, M., Liu, S., Mescua J., Yagupsky D., Quinteros, J., Giambiagi L., Sobolev, V., Strecker, M., Rodriguez Piceda C., The influence of variations in crustal composition and lithospheric strength on the evolution of the Southern Central Andean deformation: Insights from geodynamic models. <i>International Journal of Earth Sciences</i>
2021	Rodriguez Piceda, C., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Bott, J., Prezzi, C.B. & Strecker M., Lithospheric density structure of the southern Central Andes constrained by 3D data-integrative gravity modelling. <i>International Journal of Earth Sciences</i>
2020	Franceschinis, P. R., Escayola, M. P., Rapalini, A. E., Rodriguez Piceda, C. , Age constraints on the Cambrian Mesón Group (NW Argentina) based on detrital zircons U–Pb geochronology and magnetic polarity bias. <i>Journal of South American Earth Sciences</i>
2020	Franceschinis, P. R., Fazzito, S., Rapalini, A. E., Escayola, M. P., Geuna, S., Rodriguez Piceda, C . Permian remagnetization of the Early Cambrian Guachos Formation, Eastern Cordillera, Argentina. <i>Journal of South American Earth Sciences</i>

Franceschinis, P.R., Rapalini, A.E., Escayola, M.P. & Rodriguez Piceda, C.

New paleomagnetic constraints. *Tectonophysics*

Paleogeographic and tectonic evolution of the Pampia Terrane in the Cambrian:

2018 Rodriguez Piceda, C., Franceschinis, P., Escayola, M., & Rapalini, A. Paleomagnetismo del Grupo Santa Victoria en la sierra de Mojotoro, Salta: aportes a la reconstrucción paleogeográfica de Pampia en el Paleozoico temprano. *Revista de la Asociación Geológica Argentina*

• OTHER PUBLICATIONS (SCIENTIFIC CONFERENCES, DATA PUBLICATIONS)

- **Rodriguez Piceda C.**, Mildon Z., Yin Y., Andrews B., Sgambato C., van den Ende M., Ampuero J.P., *Simulating normal fault interactions during complex seismic sequences in the southern Apennines* [conference-abstract], EGU 2024 General Assembly
- 2024 Mildon Z., Andrews B., Rodriguez Piceda C., Diercks M. Insights into fault behaviour and seismic hazard from studying active and inactive faults over a range of timescales [conference-abstract], EGU 2024 General Assembly
- Andrews B., Mildon Z., Diercks M., Mitchell S., Roberts G., **Rodriguez Piceda C**, Robertson .. Using fracture-scarp lineations as kinematic indicators on active normal fault scarps [conference-abstract], EGU 2024 General Assembly
- **Rodriguez Piceda, C.**, Mildon, Z., van den Ende, M., and Ampuero, J. P. *The effects of 3D normal fault interactions in seismic cycles* [conference-abstract], EGU 2023 General Assembly
- **Rodriguez Piceda, C.,** Mildon, Z., van den Ende, M., and Ampuero, J. P: *Fault network geometry induces complex seismic sequences in normal faults*. [conference-abstract]. ICTP Workshop on Mechanics of the Earthquake Cycle
- 2023 Pons, M., Rodriguez Piceda, C., Sobolev, S. V., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., and Strecker, M. R.: *Understanding the role of structural inheritance and flat slab geometry in Central Andes* [conference-abstract], EGU 2023 General Assembly
- **Rodriguez Piceda C.** Thermomechanical state of the southern Central Andes: implications for active deformation patterns in the transition from flat to steep subduction [dissertation for PhD degree], University of Potsdam
- **Rodriguez Piceda, C.,** Gao, Y., Cacace M., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Bott, J., Tilmann, F., & Strecker M., Contributions of lithospheric structure, mantle hydration and slab flexure in seismic localization in the southern Central Andes [conference-abstract], PATADays 2022
- Götze, H.J., Bott, J., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Gomez Garcia A., **Rodriguez Piceda, C.**, Meeßen, C., Plonka, C., Spooner, C., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Schmidt S. & Anikiev, D., *Interdisciplinary data-constrained 3-D potential field modelling with IGMAS+* [conference-abstract], DGG 2021
- Anikiev, D., Götze, H.J., Bott, J., Gómez-García, À., Gomez Dacal, M. L., Meeßen, C., Spooner, C., **Rodriguez Piceda, C**., Plonka, C., Schmidt, S., Scheck-Wenderoth, M. *Interdisciplinary data-constrained 3-D potential field modelling with IGMAS+* [conference-abstract], EGU 2021 General Assembly
- **Rodriguez Piceda, C.,** Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Bott, J., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Pons, M., Prezzi, C.B. & Strecker M., *Unravelling the thermal state of the southern Central Andes and its controlling factors* [conference-abstract], EGU 2021

Rodriguez Piceda, C., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Bott, J., Prezzi, C.B. & Strecker M., *Lithospheric density structure of the Southern Central Andes and their forelands constrained by 3D gravity modelling* [conference-abstract], EGU 2020 General Assembly

Schmidt S., Anikiev, D., Götze, H.J., Gomez Garcia A., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Meeßen, C., Plonka, C., **Rodriguez Piceda, C.,** Spooner, C. & Scheck-Wenderoth, M., I*GMAS+ – a tool for interdisciplinary 3D potential field modelling of complex geological structures* [conference-abstract], EGU 2020

General Assembly

Rodriguez Piceda, C., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Bott, J., Prezzi, C.B. & Strecker M., *Lithospheric-scale 3D model of the Southern Central Andes* [dataset], GFZ data services

Rodriguez Piceda, C., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Bott, J., Prezzi, C.B. & Strecker M., *Lithospheric-scale 3D configuration of the Southern Central Andes* [conference-abstract], 5th International Young Earth Scientists (YES) Congress, Berlin, Germany

Rodriguez Piceda, C., Scheck-Wenderoth, M., Gomez Dacal, M.L., Bott, J., Prezzi, C.B. & Strecker M., Insights on the lithospheric density structure of the Southern Central Andes and their foreland [conference-abstract], 25th Latin-American Colloquium (LAC), Hamburg, Germany

2018 Rodriguez Piceda, C., Geología y paleomagnetismo del Grupo Santa Victoria en la Sierra de Mojotoro, provincia de Salta (Geology and paleomagnetism of Santa Victoria Group in the Mojotoro range, Salta Province), University of Buenos Aires [dissertation for degree]

GRANTS

ARIES Summer Research Experience Placement grant to supervise a Msc Student for six weeks at University of Plymouth (£4200)

AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

2012-2017 Roberto Rocca Foundation Scholarship for new Engineering and Geoscience undergraduate students with high academic degrees
 2016 Santander Iberoamérica Scholarship for students with high academic degrees to carry out an academic exchange in the National Autonomous University of Mexico (USD 1500)
 2015 First mention in poster competition meeting of Geology and Paleontology students, University of Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, Argentina

SUPERVISING

ARIES Summer Research Experience Placement supervising a Msc Student for six weeks at University of Plymouth

INVITED TALKS AND SEMINARS

Concepcion, Chile. Invited keynote speaker

SERVICES TO THE SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY

PEER REVIEW

- Nature communications Earth and Environment
- Geophysical Research Letters
- Tectonophysics
- International Journal of Earth Sciences

SESSION ORGANIZATION AND CHAIRING

2024 **EGU GA** Integrated approaches to seismotectonic studies

IT SKILLS

Python, Fortran (notions), MATLAB (notions), linux and bash scripting, git, High Performance Computing (SLURM), reservoir software (Petrel), data analysis software (Paraview), Finite Element Method software (GOLEM, LYNX), boundary element method software (QDYN), forward gravity modelling software (IGMAS+), Geographic Information Systems (QGIS, Global Mapper, ArcGIS), design tools (Adobe Illustrator, Inkscape)

LANGUAGES

Spanish Native **English Professional** German Intermediate (B1), University of Potsdam, Germany French Beginner (A2)

OUTREACH

2023-present	 Chief co-editor EGU Geodynamics blog Manage team of 15 editors, columnists and illustrators Edit and write weekly blog posts related to Geodynamics and Academia
2023-present	 Science Demonstrator in Plymouth University, UK Demonstrations to Secondary School students about earthquake science Demonstrator and field trip assistant in Girls into Geoscience initiative
2016-2018	 Science Communicator in Centro Cultural de la Ciencia, Buenos Aires, Argentina Organized lectures, guided tours and workshops addressed to students and public in general in an interactive science museum Had weekly training about didactics and science popularization

2015-2018 Science communicator in University of Buenos Aires Argentina Lecture on climate change, Sedimentology and Geophysics adressed to

middle-school students in outreach events organized by the university

2017	 Mentor in the 'Science Challenge' Hackathon, Buenos Aires, Argentina Mentored senior-school students which were asked to make a project related with space sciences
2014-2015	Science Communicator in Tecnópolis, Buenos Aires, Argentina Organized guided tours in science theme park
2013-2015	Volunteering. Tuition for senior school and university students in disadvantaged neighborhoods organized by the University Torcuato Di Tella, Buenos Aires, Argentina

TRAINING

ATTENDED WORKSHOPS AND COURSES

2023	Workshop on mechanics of the earthquake cycle, ICTP, Trieste, Italy
2022	COMET OpenQuake Workshop , University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom
2021	MATLAB recipes for Earth Sciences, University of Potsdam, Potsdam, Germany
2020	Tectonics modelling tutorial with ASPECT, Computational Infrastructure for Geodynamics (CIG)
2019	Solid Earth Summer School University of Grenoble, Barcelonette, France
2019	DeArGeoNet - LIDAR field methods and digital data analysis , University of Potsdam, Buenos Aires, Argentina
2018	Educational Problems, University of Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, Argentina
2018	Magnetic fabric of natural materials , University of Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, Argentina
2017	3GEO Hazard & risk analysis , CITEDEF and University of Potsdam, Buenos Aires Argentina
2015	Core analysis, YPF Foundation, Buenos Aires Argentina

ATTENDED FIELD COURSES

2019	IRTG StRATEGy, NW Argentina: geomorphology and neotectonics in the Andes
2015	Neuquén Basin, Argentina: mapping, seismic and log data analysis
2015	Martín García Island, Argentina: Geophysical Prospection
2015	San Juan, Argentina: Tectonics
2013	Tandil, Argentina: mapping
2014	Neuquén Basin, Argentina: mineralogy, paleontology and structural geology
2012	Mendoza, Argentina: sedimentology and petrology